So what I think the best thing to do
would be to share my screen, to read Dr.
Mazumdar’s work.
And unfortunately
he could not be here today.
“Small
Changes, Large Effects: A Chaos Theory
Framework for Electronic Literature
and Climate Change
for Indian Primary Students.” Dr.
Mumtaz Mazumdar.
And he is at the M.
C. Das College.
And I will put his email into the chat
after.
The challenges: In Delhi,
under teen children
ask why the playground is too hot.
In another part of India, children
wonder why monsoons arrive late.
In Mumbai, children may question
why they must wear a mask to school.
Indian children are not learning
about climate change as a future threat
but they are living it now.
Climate education for tweens faces
fundamental challenges like how do we make
invisible processes like greenhouse gases
visible and apprehensive to them?
How do we connect local observations
to the global systems?
How do we cultivate hope and agency
among constantly adding
new children than anxiety?
The answer is: effective climate education
requires multiple approaches.
There are outdoor observation,
hands-on experiments,
community engagement,
traditional instruction, and so on.
As in mathematical chaos
theory, slight changes
in the initial stages
bring significant impact later, similarly
slight changes
introduced into the syllabus
in primary classes
in Indian schools can groom
highly sensitized
climate conscious citizens in the future.
Today, my paper examines
how electronic literature
imbibed in the primary syllabus
can also contribute a potential component
within this pedagogical ecosystem,
to address specific challenges unlike the
aforesaid bland
and less triggering,
less triggering methods.
Chaos theory
or the butterfly effect is applicable
to academic or social phenomenon
because when we analyze human behavior,
we can witness how a single photo
or negative comment in the social networks
can trigger hundreds
or thousands of comments underneath.
Coming back to the Indian context, it's
well known that India;s
National Curriculum Framework
established environmental studies
as one of the core subjects for primary
classes—these are ages 6 to 11—in
the schools, emphasizing experiential
learning and local contextualization.
In these classes, climate concepts
progress are discussed developmentally.
Most of the time, classes one
through two observe weather in seasons.
Class three learns about air and water
resources.
Class four explorers seasons.
Class five brings forth
impacts on climate change on humans.
These over-young school
children are temporarily and spatially
disconnected to climate’s
delayed consequences and emissions
from power plants
affecting local air quality.
And the un-updated knowledge in textbooks
is just time-bound information.
The children also struggled
to grasp the causation
of time and distance of these phenomenon.
Whereas, unlike the unpredictable
Lyapunov timescale,
the inclusion of the climate e-literature
in the primary Indian
schools can be resultant-expected
and more deterministic in nature.
Climate
education has also to balance honesty
about challenges
with age-appropriate hope.
Research confirms
that apocalyptic messaging
induces anxiety rather than agency.
But witnessing the fast changes
in climate change,
children deserve accurate information
about their climate reality.
So here electronic literature
can contribute through interactive
digital narratives using multimodality
and computational processes, addressing
these climate challenges when integrated
with other teaching methods.
The children can visualize the former
tacit knowledge through an animated e-lit.
The climate change brainded in e-lit
can have
compulsory practical unit in the syllabus.
For example, class
five could be introduced with learning
greenhouse effects, through an interactive
narrative showing sunlight
becoming heat, encountering CO2, carbon
dioxide
molecules bouncing back to Earth.
Children can apprehend carbon
dioxide levels and observed
temperature changes
making invisible cause–effect
relationships
experientially comprehensible.
Hypertext structure can enable navigation
between scales.
A class four narrative about monsoons
may begin with local rain observations,
links to regional atmospheric patterns,
and connect to global ocean temperatures.
This mirrors how climate
actually functions and interconnects
across scales while allowing children
to explore at their own pace,
moving from familiar local contexts
toward systemic understanding.
Research confirms multimedia
animations help children understand
abstract concepts
by depicting and concrete
depicting and concreting them.
Studies also show
interactive media positively influences
pro-environment attitudes
and behavioral intentions.
However, it is also to be noted here
that exploring e-lit’s
interactivity has a limitation
for these school children.
For example, a class three student's
institutionalized e-lit may have static
climate information only in a country
or world with constant changing
air quality and industrial practices
with their consequences.
The animated series need to be annually
updated as each year new
children will be promoted in
each primary class, from class
one to class five.
Students can track monsoon arrival and
rainfall, compare with historical data,
investigate the non=linear climate’s
effects on different livelihoods, and
analyze graphs through multimodal stories
which can help them understand
regional systems with local variations.
Calculating carbon footprints
through animation
can be introduced in class five primary.
Units like creating a simulation
where the children govern
a fictional district
making climate-related
decisions and observing outcomes
could be introduced.
Students can be provided the opportunities
to create their own digital
climate stories
documenting local observations,
synthesizing their learning
through creative production.
A computer lab
in each school is a parallel
must for these climate content
practical units.
The teachers of primary classes
need to be competent in climate knowledge
with good graded certificates
in technical skills with e-lit tools.
India's existing National Initiative
for School Heads’ and Teachers’
Holistic Advancement
(NISHTHA) professional development
program offers potential infrastructure
for this preparation.
The primary children need face-to-face
learning from such trained teachers
for sharing the [different?]
climate resources.
These small or micro academic variables
introduced
at the initial
and primary stages of school can amplify
into creating more sensitized
climate conscious citizens’
trajectory in India.
The chaos theory has non-linear
determinants for results in the long run.
The determinants of inclusion of e-lit
in Indian primary classes is linear
as the climate units in the syllabus
can be introduced class-wise ‘attractors’
and the outcome will
hopefully be fruitful
in evolving climate citizens.
So I will stop sharing my screen there
and basically say, unfortunately, Dr.
Mazumdar could not be with us today
and I did have limited email with him
and he's like, “Yeah, this is a dream.
Present my ideas to the community—on
a recorded line—and see what we can
come up with.” And the wonderful tools
that you both have shown
with the Twine games— with Inky.
Those are great tools.
I was also going to introduce
to him Lyle Skains’ “No World 4 Tomorrow,”
and Lyle, I can never find your book,
so I always go to Wikipedia
and just search “No World 4 Tomorrow.”
Oh, and I was going to put in
his email, so I just put in Dr.
Mazumdar's email.
So if we come up with ideas for him,
if anyone knows of anyone
who could help
create this interactive almost database.